Guide to the Eugene V. Debs Papers TAM.020
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Eugene V. Debs Papers
1886-1966
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926
Cooper, Marguerite Debs
De Ford, Miriam Allen, 1888-1975
TAM.020
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Eugene V. Debs was president of the American Railway Union, an advocate of industrial unionism and a founding member of the Industrial Workers of the World, and a five-time candidate for president of the United States on the Socialist Party ticket. The collection, comprised of material donated to the Tamiment Library by several individuals, contains correspondence, examples of Debs' published speeches and writings, newspaper clippings, graphics, ephemera and material relating to the Eugene V. Debs Foundation. Included is a selection of material collected by Debs' attorney, Samuel Castleton, relating to Debs' imprisonment for opposition to U.S. involvement in World War I. Among the correspondents are: James Oneal, Algernon Lee, Edwin Markham and Seymour Stedman.
Custodial History
This is an assembled collection, created by Tamiment Library staff over a number of years and derived from a variety of sources. Marguerite Debs Cooper, daughter of Eugene Debs, donated materials in 1947 and in the early 1960s. Miriam Allen deFord donated materials in 1959. The Samuel Castleton Papers were donated by his daughter, Sylvia Weyl Castleton at an unknown date. The accession number 1950.159 is associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Born in Terre Haute, Indiana, to French immigrant parents, Eugene V. Debs worked as a painter on the railroad and as a clerk, while becoming active in Democratic politics at the local and state levels. He gained prominence as editor of the magazine of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen, and served as secretary-treasurer of the union. In 1893 he broke away from the conservative Brotherhood to organize the American Railway Union (ARU), one of the first industrial unions in the United States. After leading the ARU in a bitter strike against the Pullman Company in 1894, he was sentenced to six months in jail. He was among the founding members of the Industrial Workers of the World in 1905, but broke with the organization in 1908.
Debs ran for president of the United States in 1900 as the standard-bearer of the newly formed Social Democratic Party, a precursor of the Socialist Party of America. A compelling orator and charismatic leader, he was the Socialist Party's presidential candidate in 1904, 1908, 1912 and 1920.
On June 16, 1918, Debs delivered an impassioned speech in Canton, Ohio in opposition to the United States' involvement in World War I. He was arrested and tried under the Espionage Act of 1917; the indictment accused him of "attempting to cause insubordination, mutiny, disloyalty and refusal of duty within the military…. [and promoting] the cause of the Imperial German Government." He was sentenced, at the age of sixty-three, to serve ten years in federal prison. In 1920, while still imprisoned at the Atlanta Federal Penitentiary, Debs conducted his last campaign for president; he won more than 900,000 votes - 3.5 percent of the total. On December 25, 1921, President Warren G. Harding commuted Debs' sentence to time served and Debs was released from prison.
After his release, and despite his worsening health, Debs continued to speak and publish widely on behalf of the Socialist Party, and related causes such as the campaign to free Sacco and Vanzetti. He died at the age of 70 at Lindlahr Sanitarium in Elmhurst, IL on October 20, 1926, and was buried in Terre Haute.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, including some letters from Debs to James Oneal, Algernon Lee and Edwin Markham. Letters from Theodore Debs' regarding his brother are also present in the collection. Published copies of Debs' speeches and writings are also included, as are newspaper clippings and subject files. The papers of Samuel Castleton, Debs' attorney during his trial under the 1917 Espionage Act, contain correspondence and copies of Castleton's column in the Appeal to Reason entitled "Debs in Prison."
Of particular significance are materials relating to Frank X. Holl, a colleague of Debs' from the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen; the large body of correspondence between Theodore Debs and Socialist Party activist Joseph Cohen; clippings relating to the production of a Debs Medallion in 1914; subject files on Debs' "Red Special" campaign train; publicity materials from the Eugene V. Debs Foundation; and a set of playing cards with depictions of Debs and other labor leaders produced by the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into four series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence, 1899-1965
II, General Files, 1892-1966
III, Samuel Castleton Papers, 1886-1951
IV, Oversize.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Eugene V. Debs Photographs (PHOTOS 004)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This is an assembled collection, created by Tamiment Library staff over a number of years and derived from a variety of sources. Donated by Marguerite Debs Cooper, daughter of Eugene Debs, in 1947 and 1962. Another accession was donated by Miriam Allen deFord in 1959. The accession number associated with these gifts is 1950.159.
Socialists -- United States -- Biography.; Speeches.; Correspondence.; Legal documents.; Articles.; Brochures.; Trials (Sedition) |z United States.; Terre Haute (Ind.); Socialists |z United States |v Correspondence.; Labor leaders |z United States |v Correspondence.; Railroads |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Labor leaders |z United States |v Biography.; Socialist Party (U.S.); Eugene V. Debs Foundation; Brommel, Bernard J., 1930-; Germer, Adolph; Holl, Frank X.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940; Oneal, James, 1875-1962; Castleton, Samuel; Cohen, Joseph E., 1883-1950; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Debs, Theodore, 1864-1945; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen (U.S.); American Railway Union; Stedman, Seymour; Cooper, Marguerite Debs; De Ford, Miriam Allen, 1888-1975
- Series I: Correspondence, 1899-1955.
  - Cooper, Marguerite Debs: Outgoing, 1947, 1961, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Debs, Eugene V.: Outgoing, 1906-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Debs, Eugene V.: to Joseph Cohen, 1908-1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Debs, Eugene V.: to C.W. Ervin (photocopies, from Archives of Labor History and Urban Affairs, Wayne State University), 1907-1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Debs, Eugene V.: to Algernon Lee, 1907, 1918, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Debs, Eugene V.: to Edwin Markham (photocopies, from Edwin Markham Archive, Wagner College), 1899-1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Debs, Eugene V.: to James Oneal, 1910-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Debs, Katherine M.: Incoming and Outgoing, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Debs, Theodore: Outgoing, 1920-1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Debs, Theodore: to Joseph Cohen, 1917-1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Debs, Theodore: to Joseph Cohen, 1929-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Debs, Theodore: to Joseph Cohen, 1937-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Debs, Theodore: to Algernon Lee, 1914, 1920-1923, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Debs, Theodore: to James Oneal, 1921-1922, 1926-1927, 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Germer, Adolph: Incoming, 1911-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Loeb, Mitchell (re: Debs, Sacco and Vanzetti), 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Long, Fred W.: to Joseph Cohen, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lyndenberg, H. M.: to and from Algernon Lee, Mar 1927 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Moore, Samuel: to Joseph Cohen, 1920-1927 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Stedman, Seymour: Incoming, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stedman, Seymour: Outgoing, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Stone, Irving: to Joseph Cohen, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1892-1966.
  - Aldred, Guy A.: Convict 9653: America's Vision Maker, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America: Playing Cards Depicting Prominent Labor Leaders (Debs is depicted on the ace of clubs), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Articles by Debs, 1892, 1897, 1904-1906 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Articles by Debs, 1910-1916 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Articles by Debs, 1917-1926 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Articles by Debs, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Articles: "Review and Personal Statement" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Banquet in Honor of Eugene V. Debs: Program, Oct 9, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Biographical and General Information, 1920, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Brent, Joseph: "Different Characters: Roosevelt, Lincoln, Taft and Debs" (typescript), 1907 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Brommel, Bernard J.: Articles, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Brommel, Bernard J.: Interviews and Notes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Brommel, Bernard J.: Research Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1904, 1910, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Clippings, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Clippings, 1955-1959, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Clippings: Articles by James Oneal, 1920-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: Debs Medallion, Apr 5, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Eugene V. Debs Foundation, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Coldwell, Joseph M.: My Life in Prison With Debs, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Conscience of America: The Years Between (teleplay, typescript), Feb 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cooke, Edmund Vance: "Eugene" (poem), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cummings, Mary Vincent: "Memories of Girard, Kansas, Eugene V. Debs and Me", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Debs Amnesty Committee: What Did Debs Say?, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Debs Amnesty Committee: Unlock That Cell!, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Debs, Katherine Metzel: Obituary, Dec 12, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Debs Meeting Committee: Correspondence, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Debs Meeting Committee: Ephemera, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Debs Meeting Committee: Financial, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Debs Meeting Committee: General, 1923-1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Eugene V. Debs Foundation: Brochures, 1963-1966, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Eugene V. Debs Foundation: Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Eugene V. Debs Foundation: Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Eugene V. Debs v. United States of America (United States Supreme Court): Brief for Plaintiffs in Error, Oct 1918 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Eugene V. Debs v. United States of America (United States Supreme Court): Certificate in Support of Petition for Rehearing, Oct 1918 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Eugene V. Debs v. United States of America (United States Supreme Court): Petition for Rehearing, Oct 1918 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Flower, J. Howard: At Death of Debs: The Modern Knight of Man, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Free Press: Special Debs Edition, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Freund, Ernst: "The Debs Case and Freedom of Speech" (The New Republic), May 3, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Friends of Debs Column: Why the Debs Column?, [1936] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Harris, Ellis B.: Debs the Dreamer (poem), undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Harvard Summer School News: "Inside Story of Debs War Arrest Bared by Miller", Jul 15, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Holmes, John Haynes: The Riddle of Amnesty, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hook, Sidney: A Gallant American Rebel (Review of The Bending Cross: A Biography of Eugene Victor Debs), Jul 17, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hughan, Jesse Wallace: Our 'Gene, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hurt, Walter: Eugene V. Debs: An Introduction, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Karsner, David: Debs in 1920 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - LaPrade, Ruth: To His Oppressors (poem), undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - London, Jack: "The Dream of Debs," adapted for radio by Harold L. Saks, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - MacLean, Isabel: The Religious Life of Eugene V. Debs, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Meeting Notices for the Release of Debs, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Miller, Martin H.: A Tribute to a Great American, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Civil Liberties Bureau: The Law of the Debs Case, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Nearing, Scott: The Debs Decision (Rand School of Social Science pamphlet), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - The New Justice: Special Debs Number, Apr 1, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Obituaries, Oct 1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Orr, Rev. Hugh Robert: The Last Christian: Eugene V. Debs (sermon), 1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Paulish, John and Frank P. Zeidler: Spirit of Gene Debs: March (musical score), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Publications: Childhood, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Publications: Debs' Address to the Jury and Statement to the Court, Sep 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Publications: Debs and the War, Sep 1918 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Publications: Debs on the Pacific Coast, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publications: Eugene V. Debs: The Man and His Work (one copy autographed), Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Publications: Eugene V. Debs: The Voice of Labor, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publications: Eugene Victor Debs, The Champion of the American Working-Class, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Publications: Liberty, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publications: Martyred Apostles of Labor, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Publications: Personal Notes and Recollections, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Publications: Roosevelt's Heartless Tyranny, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Publications: Socialist Unity, Jun 1920 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Publications: The Children of the Poor, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Publications: The Debs Trilogy: Man, Woman, Child, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Publications: The Mission of the Socialist Party, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Publications: Tribute of Love to His Father and Mother, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Publications: "Winning a World", 1905 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Publications: Woman - Comrade and Equal, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Red Special Campaign Train, 1908, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Resolution on Release of Eugene V. Debs and Other Political Prisoners, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Robinson, Arthur: The Great Dreamer, Nov 20 1926 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Socialist Call: Debs Centennial Issue, Oct 1955 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Socialist Party: The Heritage of Debs: The Fight Against War, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Speeches, 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Speeches: Canton Speech, Jun 16, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Speeches: Industrial Unionism, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Stedman, Seymour: Closing Statement (excerpt, typescript), undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Stokes, J. G. Phelps: Reasons for Supporting Mr. Debs, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Swinton, John: 1860 - Lincoln; Debs - 189 5 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Taft, William H.: Ex-President Taft on Eugene V. Debs, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Tamiment Institute Library Bulletin: Eugene Victor Debs Birthday Issue, Dec 1960 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Terrell, Joseph Z: "The Imprisonment of Eugene V. Debs" (typescript), undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Thomas, Norman: Eugene Victor Debs, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - United States of America v. Eugene Debs (Michigan Circuit Court): Bill for Injunction, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - United States of America v. Eugene Debs (US District Court, Ohio): Copy of Indictment, Jun 1918 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Unsigned Articles, 1918-1966 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Unsigned Typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - "Winning a World" Speech Recording: Clippings and Correspondence, 1905-1913, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Series III: Castleton Papers, 1886-1951.
  - Castleton, Samuel: "Debs in Prison" (Column in Appeal to Reason), 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Chuca Choo! Song of the American Railway Union, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence: Allen, Ruth A. to Samuel Castleton, Jun 1945 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence: Babcock, Charles H. to Frank X. Holl, 1902, 1913, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence: Branstetter, Otto to Samuel Castleton, Feb 5, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence: Burke, Myrtle J. to Samuel Castleton, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence: Burton, S. D. to Samuel Castleton, Oct 27, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence: Castleton, Samuel, Outgoing (typescript copies), 1920, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence: Debs, Eugene to Adolph Germer (typescript copies), 1902-1913 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence: Debs, Eugene to Frank X. Holl, 1885-1912 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Debs, Theodore to Samuel Castleton, 1920, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Debs, Theodore to Mandel V. Halushka, Aug 4, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Debs, Theodore to Frank X. Holl, 1904-1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: DeVoe, Emma Smith to Frank X. Holl, Dec 14, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Fuhrberg, H. O. to Theodore Debs, Nov 5, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Germer, Adolph to Samuel Castleton, Sep 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Halushka, Mandel V. to Samuel Castleton, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Halushka, Mandel V. to Sylvia Weyl, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Holl, Frank X., Outgoing, undated, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: O'Hare, Kate Richards to Samuel Castleton, Sep 16, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Sharts, Joseph to Samuel Castleton, Sep 8, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: University of Texas Library to Samuel Castleton, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Warren, Fred D. to Frank X. Holl, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Weyl, Sylvia Castleton, Outgoing, 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Weyl, Sylvia Castleton to and from Raymond Ginger, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Weyl, Sylvia Castleton to L. B. Woodcock, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Woodcock, L. B. to Samuel Castleton, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Woodcock, L. B. to Sylvia Weyl Castleton, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Debs, Eugene: Statements for United Press (from prison), 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Holl, Frank X. (Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen): Membership Credentials, Photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Frank Holl, 1886, 1888, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Holl, Frank X.: "Reminiscences about Debs" (typescript), undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook, 1889-1936 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Oversize, 1919-1939, undated
  - The Call: Cartoon, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 069, Folder 1)
  - Card from Geo. Koop and Co-workers, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Eugene Victor Debs Foundation: Publicity Materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - House of Debs Certificates, 1930s? (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Poster, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - New Leader: Memorial Issue, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Orr, Rev. Hugh Robert: The Last Christian: Eugene V. Debs, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Portrait bust of Eugene V. Debs (painted bronze), 1922; cuid877; 1 item one bust (Item TAM.020.cuid877)
    Scope and Contents
    Artist: Moses Wainer Dykaar
    busts (figures)
  - Portrait bust of Eugene V. Debs (painted white), 1922; cuid878; 1 item one bust (Item TAM.020.cuid878)
  - Portrait bust of Eugene V. Debs, 1919; cuid857; 1 item one bust (Item TAM.020.cuid857)
    Artist: Louis Meyer
  - Portrait of Eugene V. Debs, Undated; cuid859; 1 item one painting (Item TAM.020.cuid859)
    Artist: N. B. Leisser
    Paintings (visual works)
  - Portrait of Eugene V. Debs, 1939; cuid858; 1 item one print (Item TAM.020.cuid858)
    Artist: C. C. Morrison
    photomechanical prints.
  - Portraits (by Mitchell Loeb and C.C. Morrison), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Call: Debs Supplement, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bust of Eugene Debs, undated; TAM.020.cuid15024 (Box 7, Object TAM.020.cuid15024)